{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>This man was formerly known as Colonel Trunk after an escape to the Brazilian embassy in the back of a car. This man\u2019s closest ally, Andres Rodriguez, agreed to depose this man after being threatened by grenade. The (+) Archives of Terror helped document this man\u2019s crimes during his participation in Operation Condor. Ciudad (*)</b> del Este was renamed in the honor of this man, who worked together with Brazil to build the Itaipu Dam. This man\u2019s 35 years of rule were called El Stronato. For the points, identify this leader who was born to German immigrants and ruled Paraguay in the mid 1900s.", "answer": "Alfredo<b> Stroessner</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s decision to appoint John Ernuszt as tax collector led the Union of the Three Nations to oppose him in Transylvania. Civilians honored this man as (+) \u201cthe Just\u201d after he disguised himself amongst commoners to ensure they were getting fair trials. Despite the Imperial Diet\u2019s attempt to install (*)</b> Vladislaus Jagiello, this man\u2019s victories over the Hussites secured him the title of King of Bohemia. This man established the professionalized Black Army during his reign. For the points, identify this son of Janos Hunyadi, a king who greatly expanded Hungarian military power.", "answer": "Matthias<b> Corvinus</b> (accept<b> Matthias I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This person ran for Congress after Edna Kelly sought re-election in a different district; in that election, this person defeated James Farmer\u2019s Liberal Party ticket. This person</b> <b>controversially visited (+)</b> <b>George Wallace at a hospital after his assassination attempt.</b> <b>George Wallace at a hospital after his assassination attempt.</b> <b>This person ran on the campaign slogan \u201cUnbought and (*)</b> <b>This person ran on the campaign slogan \u201cUnbought and (*)</b> Unbossed\u201d, which also titles her memoir. In 1972, this person became the first woman to run for the Democratic Party presidential nomination. For the point, name this first black elected to Congress, doing so in New York\u2019s 12th district in 1968.", "answer": "Shirley<b> Chisholm</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>At the end of a film by this director, the elderly Kane attempts to save her dead husband from a non-existent explosion. This director of</b><em><b> Rhapsody in August</b></em><b>, oversaw a film in which a (+) woodcutter finds, and takes home, an abandoned infant. This director\u2019s ability to tell a story from its \u201clowliest characters\u201d inspired George Lucas to have (*) </b> C-3PO and R2-D2 drive the plot of Star Wars. This man created an adaptation of<em> MacBeth</em> titled<em> Throne of Blood</em> which starred Toshiro Mifune. In a film by this director, a group of warriors defend a town from bandits during the Sengoku period. For the points, name this Japanese director responsible for<em> Rashoman</em> and<em> Seven</em> <em>Samurai</em>.", "answer": "Akira<b> Kurosawa</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b>One of this movement\u2019s goals was eventually recognized in the Nine Power Treaty. This movement opposed the Twenty-One Demands. Chen Duxiu helped lead this movement, which drove him towards Marxism. This movement turned the (+) New Culture Movement political and adopted the ideals of \u201cMr. Science\u201d and \u201cMr. Democracy.\u201d This movement was sparked by Japan receiving the former German (*) </b> concession of Qingdao, known as the Shandong Problem. For the points, name this student-led movement which criticized China\u2019s diplomatic failure in the Treaty of Versailles.", "answer": "<b> May 4th</b> Movement (or<b> \u201cwusi yundong\u201d</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>A fictional merchant from this city jumped into the sea to appease the Sea Tsar and married the mermaid Chernava, who turned into a river. This home of Sadko held the (+) easternmost outpost of the Hanseatic League and fought a series of wars against Sweden for control of the Gulf of Finland. One leader from this city defeated the Swedish at the Battle of the (*) </b> Neva before defeating the Bishop of Dorpat and the Livonian Order on Lake Peipus at the Battle on the Ice. For the points, name this Russian city which was eventually eclipsed and conquered by its rival, Moscow, and which was the home of Alexander Nevsky.", "answer": "Veliky<b> Novgorod</b> (do not prompt on or accept \u201cNizhny Novgorod\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In a speech during this trial, the defense attorney compared power to a \u201cgreat river\u201dand declared liberty to be the \u201cbest cause\u201d. During this trial, Richard Bradley denied that the prosecution was advocating for punishments similar to those of the notorious (+) Court of the Star Chamber. The defense attorney in this trial would later plan the construction of Independence Hall. Justice James DeLancey oversaw this trial, which was prompted by the removal of Judge (*) </b> Lewis Morris. In this trial, the editor of the New York Weekly Journal was defended by Andrew Hamilton against libel accusations leveled by Governor William Cosby. For the points, name this colonial-era trial centering on the namesake German-American newspaper editor.", "answer": "John Peter<b> Zenger</b> Trial (accept Crown v. John Peter<b> Zenger</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Igor Kostin photographed a helicopter flying over a site just outside this city in preparation for incoming \u201cliquidators.\u201dAn oft-photographed (*) </b> Ferris wheel in this city was scheduled to open for May Day celebrations but was permanently delayed when the city was evacuated due to an April 1986 disaster. For the points, name this Ukrainian town which was constructed to house workers from the Chernobyl Nuclear plant.", "answer": "<b> Pripyat</b> (do not accept or prompt on Chernobyl)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "For the points, name this family of Pakistani politicians, whose most notable members included Zulfiqar Ali and his daughter Benazir.", "answer": "<b> Bhutto</b> family (accept Zulfiqar Ali<b> Bhutto</b>; accept Benazir<b> Bhutto</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In this work, a character observes people ballroom dancing prompting them to write the essay \u201cA World Without Collisions.\u201d The title character of this play suggests Charles Darwin and not Napoleon is a (+) \u201cman of magnitude.\u201d This play is set while a character\u2019s father is attempting to be discharged from a hospital. A character in this play can\u2019t pay for a (*) </b> jukebox because he must pay for his bus fare home, and is preparing for a ballroom dance contest with Hilda. Characters reminisce about flying a kite and a Hallie spits in the face of Sam in, for the points, what Apartheid-era play by Athol Fugard?", "answer": "<b> Master Harold...and the Boys</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b>These organizations gained protection from the Ordinances of Justice. The Le Chapelier Law and the Combination Act banned these organizations in France and Britain. Many of</b> <b>London\u2019s (+)</b> <b>livery companies originated from these organizations. People barred from</b> <b>livery companies originated from these organizations. People barred from</b> <b>joining these organizations supported Michele di Lando during the (*)</b> <b>joining these organizations supported Michele di Lando during the (*)</b> Florentine<em> ciompi</em> revolt. Members of these institutions started as apprentices, then became journeymen and finally master craftsmen. For the points, name these associations of artisans and merchants, the precursor to modern trade unions.", "answer": "<b> Guild</b>s (prompt on<b> union</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Bernard Cohen and Philip Hirschkop filed a motion that elevated this case. Earl Warren called an action central to this case \u201cfundamental to our very existence and survival\u201d and</b> <b>part of the (+)</b> <b>\u201cbasic civil rights of man\u201d. One person in this case actually was of</b> <b>Indian-Rappahannock ancestry instead of her presumed African-American heritage. This case overruled the decisions in the (*)</b><em> Monks</em> case and in<em> Pace v. Alabama</em>. This case was brought up due to a violation of Virginia\u2019s 1924 Racial Integrity Act. Laws banning interracial marriage were nullified in, for the points, what 1967 Supreme Court civil rights case?", "answer": "<b> Loving</b> v. Virginia", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This city is home to Saint Elijah\u2019s Monastary which closed in 1743 after all the momks were killed by attacking Persians. A mosque in this city contained a minaret known as (+)</b> <b>\u201cIraq\u2019s Tower of Pisa\u201d because the minaret was leaning. A house in this city was where Saddam Hussein\u2019s sons Uday and Qusay were killed. ISIS once controlled the (*) </b> Ninawa International Hotel in this city, which resides directly opposite from Nineveh on the bank of the Tigris River. For the point, what Iraqi city was captured alongside Fallujah by ISIS in 2014 until it was liberated in 2017?", "answer": "<b> Mosul</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>A gold funerary mask dated to this period was discovered in Grave Circle A and was described as the \u201cMona Lisa of prehistory.\u201d The Treasury of Atreus is an example of this</b> <b>period\u2019s (+)</b> <b>tholos or beehive tombs. A system of syllabic script used during this period</b> <b>tholos or beehive tombs. A system of syllabic script used during this period</b> <b>was deciphered by Michael Ventris and is known as (*)</b> <b>was deciphered by Michael Ventris and is known as (*)</b> Linear B. The Dorian Invasion during the Bronze Age Collapse is thought to have contributed to this period\u2019s demise. For the points, name this preclassical period of Ancient Greece that saw the reign of king Agamemnon.", "answer": "<b> Mycenae</b>en period", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Because the victorious side in this battle was busy looting almost a thousand chariots, the losing side managed to defend the namesake fortress during a seven-month siege until the King of (+) Kadesh fled. A commander at this battle rejected his generals\u2019 advice and marched through the town of Aruna via a narrow ravine. (*)</b> Tjaneni kept careful records of this battle, which were later used to carve victory inscriptions in the Temple of Amun-Ra at Karnak. For the points, name this 15th century BC engagement between the Canaanites and Egyptians led by pharaoh Thutmose III, the earliest recorded battle in history.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Megiddo</b> (accept Siege of<b> Megiddo</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This city created the first municipal zoning ordinance in the U.S. in 1908. This city\u2019s Terminal Island built over 300 Liberty Ships after its shipyard\u2019s construction in 1941. The</b> <b>collapse of the (+)</b> <b>St. Francis Dam near this city ended the career of a civil engineer</b> <b>responsible for creating this city\u2019s namesake \u201cAqueduct\u201d, which fueled this city\u2019s growth post-1913. Frederick (*) </b> Eaton partnered with William Mulholland to divert water from the Owens River to this city in the San Fernando Valley. For the points, name this West Coast city, the second-largest in the U.S.", "answer": "<b> Los Angeles</b> (accept<b> LA</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This monarch ordered a copy of every book printed in his kingdom in the Ordinance of Montpellier and replaced Latin with French as the administrative language of his country in the Ordinance of (+) Villers-Cotterets. This monarch ordered the massacre of Waldensians in M\u00b4erindol after turning against Protestantism in the Affair of the (*)</b> Placards. The Treaty of Madrid was rejected by this monarch after being held captive, where he wrote \u201cnothing remains to me except honor and life.\u201d Leonardo da Vinci was invited to work in France by, for the points, what monarch who lost the Battle of Pavia to Emperor Charles V?", "answer": "<b> Francis I</b> (prompt on Francis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A female member of this family opposed the Indian Removal Bill with a circular and</b> <b>called for the incorporation of kindergarten into schooling. Along with (+)</b> <b>Catherine,</b> <b>another member of this family was revealed to be having an affair by Elizabeth Woodhull and was Henry Ward. Breech loading (*)</b> Sharps rifles from New England were called this family\u2019s namesake \u201cBibles\u201d. One member of this family wrote<em> Dred, A Tale of the Great Dismal Swamp</em> and was accused by Abraham Lincoln as the \u201clittle woman\u201d who \u201cstarted this great war\u201d. For the points, name this family of abolitionists, whose members included the writer of<em> Uncle Tom\u2019s Cabin</em>.", "answer": "<b> Beecher</b> family (prompt on<b> Stowe</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The \u201cOutlaw Resolution\u201d was passed by Warren Harding in the wake of one of these events in which workers had seniority rights removed and which was ended by the (+)\u201cDaugherty Injunction\u201d. Along with one of these events in 1922, another caused Thomas Scott suggest \u201ca rifle diet...\u201d and that event of this type saw a uprising in (*)</b> Shamokin and the Reading massacre. One event of this type began in Martinsburg, West Virginia and was a response to a third wage cut by the Baltimore and Ohio. For the points, name these events, one of which took place in 1877, in which freight and passenger cars were out of action.", "answer": "Great<b> Railroad Strikes</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this conflict, the sinking of a ship commanded by Captain Galsworthy nearly</b> <b>resulted in a diplomatic incident. The Kim Ok-Gyun affair and the (+)</b> <b>Donghak Peasant</b> <b>Revolt occurred prior to this conflict during which the Battle of Pyongyang occurred. The Beiyang Fleet was decisively defeated at the Battle of the (*) </b> Yalu River during this conflict. This conflict ended with one side ceding Taiwan to the other in the Treaty of Shimonoseki. For the points, name this conflict in which the Qing Dynasty was defeated by an Asian country led by Emperor Meiji.", "answer": "<b> First Sino-Japanese War</b> (Accept War of<b> Jiawu</b>) (NHBB Nats)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This group decreed that one lawmaking organization had to meet at least once every three years in the Triennial Acts. The Five Members, including John Hampden and (+) John Pym, were members of this larger body. The Self-Denying Ordinance decreed one could be a member of this body or the army. George (*)</b> Monck restored this body and forced it to change to the Convention Parliament by reinstating members who were removed in Pride\u2019s Purge. For the points, the Rump Parliament was formed out of what governmental body that lasted throughout the English Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Long</b> Parliament (prompt on \u201cparliament\u201d before first mention of \u201cParliament\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Chief Kepuha\u2019s conversion to Catholicism on this island allowed the Spanish to build Dulce Nombre de Maria Cathedral. The Sergeant Shoichi Yokoi was found living in (+) Talofofo Cave of this island in the early 1970s, returning to Japan soon after. His superior, Lt. Gen. Hideyoshi Obata, committed seppuku at this island\u2019s Mount Mataguac after failing to hold it. This island\u2019s motto is (*)</b> \u201cLand of the Chamorros,\u201d in reference to the dominant Austronesian group that still inhabit the island. For the point, name this unincorporated territory in Micronesia ceded to the US along with the Philippines and Puerto Rico at the end of the Spanish-American War.", "answer": "<b> Guam</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>During one event, Michael Corbett told Henry Panton that if he crossed a lint of salt he would take it as proof that he was attempting to perform this action. Thomas (+) Jefferson claimed that an incident surrounding this practice put war with the British into his hands and that he only had to open them to \u201clet havoc loose.\u201d James Barron was (*) </b>court-martialed following an 1807 incident in which this practice was carried out at Hampton Roads. The Chesapeake-Leopard affair was caused by, for the points, what practice of forcing men into military service commonly carried out by the British navy?", "answer": "<b> impressment</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a 1930 proposal titled the \u201cMemorandum in the Organization of a Regime of European Federal Union\u201d, this man called for an economic union that would counter Germany\u2019s post World War One recovery. An agreement between this man and (+) Bonaventura Cerretti allowed the Vatican to nominate French diocesan bishops. A pact passed by this non-American codified the idea of a crime against peace but failed to include enforcement protocols. For helping to negotiate the (*)</b> Locarno Treaties, this man and Gustav Stresemann won the Novel Peace Prize. For the points, name this eleven term Prime Minster of France who signed a peace agreement with Frank Kellogg.", "answer": "Aristide<b> Briand</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Journalist Walter Liggett was killed in this city by a mobster who went unprosecuted by governor Floyd Olson. Kid Cann worked in this city, whose 1934 general strike was led</b> <b>by the (+)</b> <b>Teamsters. This city\u2019s Metropolitan Building was demolished along with most</b> <b>of its Gateway District in the 1950s. Lincoln (*)</b> Steffens exposed the \u201cShame\u201d of this city in an article attacking its four-term mayor \u201cDoc\u201d Ames. This city in Hennepin County is the larger of the Twin Cities. For 10 points, name this Midwestern city located adjacent to its state\u2019s capital of St. Paul.", "answer": "<b> Minneapolis</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}